Clinton A. Carpenter Papers, 1923–1997 (bulk 1951–1997)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
Clinton A. Carpenter Papers
1923–1997
1951–1997
Carpenter, Clinton A., 1921-2005
4.5 cubic feet (9 boxes)
Archives and Special Collections Library, Vassar College Libraries
The papers of Clinton A. Carpenter center on his work as a composer, specifically his interpretation of Gustav Mahler's 10th Symphony. The materials include correspondence, subject files, musical scores, typescripts, Mahler-related newsletters and publications, photographic prints, press clippings, and one audio recording.
Biographical Note
Clinton A. Carpenter (1921 – 2005) was the first American composer to complete Mahler’s unfinished Tenth Symphony. A Chicago native, Carpenter was employed as an insurance underwriter, with a life-long commitment to studying the works of Gustav Mahler, in particular, Mahler’s unfinished Tenth Symphony. Carpenter attended Eastman School of Music after returning from the Army at the close of World War II, and received his degree from Eastman in 1947. Carpenter initially completed his composition of Mahler’s Tenth Symphony in 1949. By the early 1950s, as an exercise in further studying Mahler’s orchestration, Carpenter attempted to reconstruct the orchestral version of the symphony from his own studies on the piano. Carpenter later went on to compare his own orchestral page with the Mahler score to identify differences. Later versions of Mahler’s Tenth Symphony edited by Carpenter were completed in 1952, 1954, 1955 and 1957. Carpenter finished his interpretation of the symphony in 1966. In 1983, the Carpenter composition received its world premiere in Chicago, performed by the Chicago Civic Orchestra.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Clinton A. Carpenter center on his work as a composer, specifically his interpretation of Gustav Mahler's 10th Symphony. The materials include correspondence, subject files, musical scores, typescripts, Mahler-related newsletters and publications, photographic prints, press clippings, and one audio recording.
Access
This collection is open for research according to the
regulations of the Vassar College Archives and Special Collections Library
without any additional restrictions.
Subject Headings
Names:
Mahler, Gustav, 1860-1911
Subjects:
Symphonies--Scores
Document Types:
Scores (documents for music)
Titles:
Mahler, Gustav, 1860-1911. Symphonies, no. 10
VCL Categories
Music
Encoding Information
Encoded by Laura Streett, January 2018.
Acquisition Information
Transferred from the Vassar College Music Library in 2010.
Series List
- Series 1. Subject Files, 1956-1997; (Boxes 1 and 3)
  Subject files include Carpenter’s extensive documentation of his studies of Mahler’s methodologies, including typescript notations regarding Mahler’s Timing and Keys. Subject files include notes regarding Mahler’s temperament, the literature he read, a timeline of the composer’s life, studies of his handwriting, and terms used by the composer. Typed notes include Carpenter’s comparisons between Mahler and his contemporaries, with lists of performances arranged by date and musical style, including the number of performances executed during each composer’s lifetime.
- Series 2. Musical Scores, 1965-1966, undated; (Boxes 1 and 4-8)
  Musical scores include extensive performance notes, for both the conductor and musicians, following the first performance of Carpenter’s interpretation of Mahler’s 10th Symphony in 1983. Scores include, Carpenter’s own rendering of the composition, in two volumes, with notations, as well as the Paul Zsolnay publication of Mahler’s Tenth, which was Carpenter’s first introduction to the composition.
- Series 3. Typescripts, 1969-1988; (Box 1)
  Typescripts include articles written by Carpenter on Wheeler’s interpretations of the 10th symphony, and also includes Carpenter’s bio.
- Series 4. Printed Material, 1923-1995; (Boxes 1-3)
  Printed material includes a run (1956 – 1995) of the International Gustav Mahler Society Newsletter, with Carpenter’s notations.
- Series 5. Correspondence, 1956-1999; (Box 3)
  Includes incoming and outgoing correspondence.
- Series 6. Miscellaneous, circa 1960, 1983; (Boxes 1 and 9)
  Includes a scrapbook of programs, pressclippings and photographs from the world premiere of Carpenter’s composition (Chicago, 1983) and audio recording of Mahler’s 10th Symphony by the British Broadcasting BBC Broadcasting Corporation (BBC), circa 1960.
Container List
- Series 1. Subject Files
  - 10th Symphony notes and movement themes (1.10 - 1.11)
  - Carpenter inventory of archival holdings, 1996 (1.1)
  - Colorado Mahler Festival, clippings, programs, 1997 (1.2)
  - Comparisons between Mahler and contemporaries (1.5)
  - Errata, notes for 10th Symphony performance, Chicago, 1983 (1.3 - 1.4)
  - Handwriting study of Gustav Mahler (1.6)
  - International Gustav Mahler Society Annual Reports, 1956-1994 (3.6 - 3.7)
  - Orchestration and Instrumentation notes (1.7-1.9)
  - Terms used by Mahler (1.12)
  - Timeline of Mahler’s life (1.13)
  - Timing and keys, notes, 10th Symphony (1.14)
- Series 2. Musical Scores
  - Critical Edition of Total Works, Volume XI, Last Four Movements from Symphony No. 10, edited by Clinton A. Carpenter, includes additional remarks on Carpenter urtext, (bound manuscript) (7.1)
  - Critical Edition of Total Works, volume XI, Last Four Movements from Symphony No. 10, edited by Clinton Carpenter, with general comments on urtext, (facsimile) (8.1)
  - Gustav Mahler 10th Symphony, Paul Zsolnay Edition, (facsimile) (8.2-8.5)
  - Gustav Mahler X Symphonie, by Clinton A. Carpenter, Volumes I, II, including performance notes, (manuscript) (5.1-5.2)
  - Gustav Mahler’s Lieder und Gesange, Vol. 3, (facsimile) (7.3)
  - Gustav Mahler’s Symphony No. 10, (facsimile) (7.4)
  - Mahler Symphony No. 10, Part I, Part II, interpreted by Clinton A.Carpenter, (manuscript) (6.1-6.2)
  - Mahler Symphony No. 10, transcribed for Piano-Four Hands, by Clinton A. Carpenter, (manuscript) (6.3)
  - Mahler, The Youth’s Magic Horn, No. 220, Wiener Philharmonischer, 1966; (photocopy) (1.21)
  - Mahler’s 10th Symphony-Carpenter, 1st and 2nd movements, (manuscript) (4.1-4.2)
  - Mahler’s 10th Symphony, Carpenter score, (photocopy) (1.16-1.19)
  - Mahler’s 10th Symphony, Cooke Version, 2 Piano Version, Bowman, (photocopy) (4.3)
  - Mahler’s 10th Symphony, Freidrich Block, Piano Arrangements 2, 4 and 5th movements, (photocopy) (4.4)
  - Mahler’s 10th Symphony, Performing Edition by Joe Wheeler, 1965; (annotated photocopy) (4.5)
  - Mahler’s 9th Symphony, Erwin Ratz score, (photocopy) (1.20)
  - Study of Mahler’s Das Klagende Lied, by Alfred Rose, (photocopy) (1.15)
  - Theme in 5th Movement As Might Be Written by Von Webern-A Satire, (manuscript) (7.2)
- Series 3. Typescripts
  - Mahler’s 10th Symphony — articles written by Clinton Carpenter, 1969-1988 (1.22)
  - Mahler Werke Verzeichnis — index of performances, including commentary (1.23-1.24)
  - Wheeler version of Mahler’s 10th Symphony — article for Journal of the Conductor’s Guild, by Clinton Carpenter, circa 1983 (1.25)
- Series 4. Printed Material
  - Gustav Mahler, A Performing Version of the draft for the 10th Symphony, by Deryck Cooke, 1966 (3.12)
  - International Gustav Mahler Society Newsletter, 1956-1995 (2.1-2.19)
  - Mahler clippings, articles, programs, 1923-1992 (3.8-3.11)
  - Mahler, Symphony No. 10, Associated Music Publishers, 1951 (3.13)
  - Mahler, Symphony No. 10, Adagio, Universal Edition, 1964, 1990; (2 copies) (3.14)
  - News About Mahler Research, publication by the International Gustav Mahler Society, 1977-1995 (1.29-1.30)
- Series 5. Correspondence
  - Correspondence to Clinton Carpenter re: Mahler Symposium, Utrecht, 1986 (3.1)
  - Correspondence, to and from Clinton Carpenter, 1956-1999 (3.2-3.3)
  - Nieman, Herman, Secretary of Gustav Mahler Society, 1957- 1992 (3.4)
  - Nikkels, Dr. Eveline, 1989-1994 (3.5)
- Series 6. Miscellaneous
  - Scrapbook — world premiere of Carpenter performance of Mahler’s 10th Symphony, Chicago, 1983-04 (1.26-1.28)
  - Audio recording — Mahler’s 10th Symphony, BBC Broadcast, Deryck Cooke, circa 1960; (quarter-inch audio tape reel) (Box 9)